

Daniel Felipe Ordoñez Apraez

ELLIS Ph.D Student in Bioengineering and Robotics - M.Sc. Artificial Intelligence

CONTACT

Personal website

+39 351 9861722

linkedin.com/in/danfoa

github.com/Danfoa

Google Scholar

Profile

Second year ELLIS Ph.D. student exploring the applications of group theory in robot modeling, control and design. My research strives to enhance robotic functionality through mathematically driven innovation. I have a specialized focus on the exploitation of structural/morphological symmetry groups in locomoting robotic and dynamical systems. Born in: 1995.

INTERESTS

Geometric Deep Learning

Group theory Control Theory

Differential Geometry

Dynamical System's theory

LANGUAGES

Spanish English German Italian

Mother Tonque C1 (TOEFL) Intermediate - B2 Basic

PROGRAMMING







SOFTWARE



REFERENCES

Dr. Massimiliano Pontil

ITALIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY Massimiliano.Pontil@iit.it

Dr. Mario Martin

Universitat Politècnica de CATALUNYA mmartin@cs.upc.edu

Dr. Claudio Semini

ITALIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY claudio.semini@iit.it

EDUCATION

Oct-2022/25

Genova / Edinburgh 9

Italian Institute of Technology (IIT) - University of Genova **European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems (ELLIS)**

Ph.D. IN BIOENGINEERING AND ROBOTICS

Project topic: Exploration of applications of group theory in analytical and datadriven modeling, control, and design of robotic systems

Supervisors: Dr. Massimiliano Pontil (CSML), Dr. Claudio Semini (DLS), and Dr. Carlos Mastalli (RoMi).

2019-2021

Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya - Barclona Tech

Barcelona Spain 💡

M.Sc. in Artificial Intelligence

Thesis: Learning to run naturally: quiding policies with the Spring-Loaded Inverted Pendulum

Part time researcher at the institute of Industrial Robotics and Informatics (IRI)

2013-2018

Bogota Colombia 💡

Universidad Nacional de Colombia

B.Sc. in Mechatronics Engineering - Major in Robotics **Exchange Semester:** Technical University of Munich

EXPERIENCE

2021-2022 2019-2021

Barcelona Spain 💡

Institut de Robòtica i Informàtica Industrial (IRI-CSIC)

ASSISTANT RESEARCHER STUDENT RESEARCHER

Research Projects: - Learning realistic legged locomotion by enforcing sagittal symmetry control equivariance and contact spring-mass dynamics.

- Learning human hand synergies of motion with Variational Autoencoders

2018-2019 2017-2018

Cologne Germany 9 INVITE GmbH research center (TU Dortmund & Bayer Technology Services)

JUNIOR RESEARCH ASSISTANT

ROBOTICS INTERN

Research project: Manipulation of plastic bags using a two-arm robot with 3D vision and force feedback. (see presentation video

- EP-Patent: Autonomous Drum and Inliner Handling

Publications - Patents

- [Preprint] Dynamics Harmonic Analysis of Robotic Systems: Application in Data-Driven Koopman Modeling. Ordoñez-Apraez Daniel, Kostic Vladimir, Turrisi Giulio, Novelli Pietro, Mastalli Carlos, Semini Claudio, Pontil Massimiliano. 2023
- On discrete symmetries of robotics systems: A group-theoretic and data-driven analysis. Ordonez-Apraez, Daniel - Agudo, Antonio - Moreno, Francesc - Martin, Mario. Robotics Science and Systems RSS-2023
- [Worshop] Morphological symmetries in robot learning. Ordonez-Apraez, Daniel Agudo, Antonio - Moreno, Francesc - Martin, Mario. RSS-2023 Workshop on Symmetries in Robot Learning
- An Adaptable Approach to Learn Realistic Legged Locomotion without Examples. Ordonez-Apraez, Daniel - Agudo, Antonio - Moreno, Francesc - Martin, Mario. 2022 International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)
- [Patent] Autonomous Drum and Inliner Handling. INVITE GmbH., Bayer A.G. Published European and US patent EP4112238A1/US2023009062A1.

Awards

2019 Top 1% score on the Colombian Saber-Pro national exam, which evaluates all students near graduation of a higher education's degree

2019 Selected to the Colombian COLFUTURO's recruitment of talent program and awarded scholarship/loan for higher education

University tuition exception 2015

ACADEMIC AND OPEN-SOURCE PROJECTS

- **MorphoSymm repository:** Open-access repository for exploiting morphological/structural symmetry groups in robotics
- Implementation of DeepMind's Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning model of common-pool resource appropriation
- Measuring Parkinson's disease progression
- **Protein evolution/structure prediction** Design of custom permutation invariant CNN layers targeted at processing protein's Multiple Sequence Alignments
- Transition INVITE's robotics research platform to ROS.
- Mechanic, electronic and control design of a Micromouse

Symmetries in robot modeling and control

- Mechanic and control design of a two-DoF RP robot
- ullet Control design of a 1-DoF air propelled system experimenting with different robust control techniques (H_{∞} , Slide Mode Control and Adaptive control)

TEACHING AND INVITED LECTURES

Feb 2023 Bogotá Colombia ◊	Modern techniques of machine learning and control to robotics SEMINAR - UNIVERSIDAD NACIONAL DE COLOMBIA Lecture: On the role of symmetries in machine learning and control of robotic systems
Jan-Feb 2022 Barcelona Spain ♥	Laboratories on scene reconstruction and structure from Motion M.Sc. IN COMPUTER VISION - UNIVERSITAT AUTÒNOMA DE BARCELONA Course: 3D-Vision Main Lecturer: Prof. Dr. Gloria Haro
Dec 2021 Barcelona Spain ◊	Introduction to AI for speech-language pathology students BS IN SPEECH-LANGUAGE PATHOLOGY - UNIVERSITAT AUTÒNOMA DE BARCELONA Higher cognitive functions seminar series. Main Lecturer: Prof. Paula Resina
Mar-Dec 2016 Bogotá Colombia ◊	Universidad Nacional de Colombia ENGINEERING FACULTY TUTOR Courses tutored: - Data structures and algorithms - Numerical methods - Control theory - Object-oriented programming - Basic programming

PRESENTATIONS

Oct 2023

Berkley US ♀	REMOTE SEMINAR PRESENTATION: SLIDES HYBRID ROBOTICS LABORATORY UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, BERKELEY
May 2023 London UK ♀	Morphological Symmetries in Robot Learning SPOTLIGHT WORKSHOP PRESENTATION: YOUTU.BE/VXTKCBNNU8M ICRA-2023 WORKSHOP ON EFFECTIVE REPRESENTATIONS, ABSTRACTIONS, AND PRIORS FOR ROBOT LEARNING (RAP4Robots)
May 2023 Daegu Korea §	Morphological Symmetries in Robot Learning Workshop Presentation: youtu.be/E2L16T0biu4 RSS-2023 Workshop on Symmetries in Robot Learning
Dec 2021 Barcelona Spain ♥	An Adaptable Approach to Learn Realistic Legged Locomotion without Examples Poster at Deep Learning Barcelona Symposium